欢迎回到格式化字符串漏洞系列
welcome back to our series here on format strings and format string exploits
在这个视频中我们要讨论
in this video we're going to discuss
printf如何使用格式化字符串来写数据
how format strings can be used with printf to write data
用printf来写数据，这听起来确实很怪
now writing data with the print function certainly sounds a little bit strange
怎么做呢
so how do we do it
printf实现了一个%n的替换符
well it turns out printf implements a substitution percent n
%n会对传入的指针解引用
and percent n will dereference a pointer from the stack
然后把已输出字符串的字节数写到该地址
and write the number of bytes written so far to that address
我们来看一下这个例子
so if we look at this example
有一个整型变量namelength
we have an integer namelength
然后调用printf("%s%n"
then we call printf percent s percent n
之后第一个参数是name
where the first parameter is name
第二个参数是namelength的地址
and the second parameter is a reference to namelength
printf运行时
when this printf command is ran
会输出name到标准输出
name will be displayed at standard out
并且已输出字节
and the number of bytes written
本例中，name的长度
which in this case is just the length of name
将写入namelength
will be stored in namelength
这样当第二次调用printf时
that way when printf is called a second time
namelength肯定是正确的
the namelength will always be correct
因为它是在第一次调用printf时被设置好的
because it is being set in the first printf
在第二次printf时使用
and used in the second printf
有的程序会正常用%n
you also see applications where percent n makes sense
当尝试实现任意一种动态格式化字符串时
when you're doing any type of dynamic formatting
你都可能会输出一些用户提供的内容
you may be printing some user provided input
但你不一定知道它有多长
and you don't necessarily know how long it is
使用%n
by using percent n
我们就可以在输出的同时，记录它的长度
we can display it and store the length at the same time
所以这个功能是有合理用途的
so there are legitimate use cases for this
然而，%n也适用于漏洞利用
however percent n is also right for exploitation
我们用一个例子来看一下它的厉害
so let's take a look at why this is bad in a demo
我从之前视频中的代码开始
so I'm gonna start off with the same code example that we had in the prior video
我要把它改成
and I'm gonna change this to be
一个能通过写入数据来获取flag的例子
an example where writing data will get us the flag
要做到这一点，我需要一个print_flag值
and to do that I'm going to have a print_flag value
初始值设为0
and we will initially set it to be 0
现在
now if
不管什么原因，如果它不是0
for whatever reason it is not 0
我们就打开/flag
then we will open the flag
将它读入某个缓冲区
read it into some buffer
然后输出到标准输出
and then we will write it to standard out
现在我们需要设置缓冲区
now we'll need to set the buffer
在这声明定义一个buf
we define the buf declare it here
就把它放在栈上
so it can just be here on the stack
我们还需要包含一些额外的头文件
and we'll need to include some additional header files
现在编译它
so now if we compile this
传入一个%x，还能看到beef1337
and we pass it percent x we still get beef1337
而且不会得到flag
and we don't get a flag
这里我们不会传入很多%p
so rather than spamming percent p
再去猜哪个是print_flag指针
and trying to guess what where is this print_flag pointer
我们直接用GDB
we're going to use GDB
调试一下，看看能不能算出来
and explore the binary and see if we can calculate it
我们开始吧
so let's do that
我们在GDB中运行程序
we will run the binary in GDB
我们在main处设置一个断点
we'll set a break point at main
现在我们在main的最开始
now right now we are at the very beginning of main
如果我们看一下
and if we look
在开始推理前，需要先执行完这个序言
we need this prologue to happen before we can start reasoning about it
因为我们想在main的栈帧中
because we want to be in the function frame of main
所以我先让它执行几条指令
so I'm going to move forward several instructions
把RBP和RSP设置好
so that RBP and RSP are set
现在如果我们反汇编main
so now if we disassemble main
我想找到在哪里发生的这个比较
I want to find where in the binary is this comparison happening
在哪里检查的print_flag
where are we checking print_flag
我们从这里往上看
and as we look up from here
我们看到这一串的open read write
we see the open read write
所以还要再上面
so it's going to be above this
看到了test eax, eax
and we have test EAX EAX
这里大概就是比较的位置
so this is very likely where that's occurring
这里检查eax是否为0
that's the check
这里跳转到输出或是不输出flag的代码块
and this is the jump that either reads the flag out or it does not
我们可以看到
and we see that
EAX为RAX, RAX为RBP-0x220
EAX is RAX and RAX is RBP-0x220
那我们输出RBP - 0x220
so let's print RBP - 0x220
另一个我感兴趣的值是RSP
and the other value I'm interested in is RSP
如果我们看这两个位置之间的距离
and if we look at the distance between these two locations
是0x20
it's hex twenty
当printf向前寻找参数时
now when printf is marching forward looking for arguments
步长为8字节（一个参数8字节）
they are all of sought length 8
用0x20除以8，得到4
which means we take 0x20 and divided by 8.  we get 4
而且第六个参数是第一个栈上参数（不算格式化字符串）
we also know that the sixth argument is the first one on the stack
就是printf返回后的RSP
that would be RSP
6 + 4 = 10
so 6 + 4 is 10
我们可以认为
so we would assume that
从printf的角度看，print_flag是它的第10个参数
the print_flag value is the 10th argument from printf or from printf's perspective here
我们来验证一下
so let's verify that
我们执行a.out
we'll run a.out
再给几个字节，接着%10$n
and we will give it just some bytes followed by percent 10 $ n
这里的a，用来随便输出几个字节
now the a(s) are here so that some bytes are written out
如果是a%10$n
if I just do a percent 10 n
将会把1写入printf第10个参数处
this should write 1 to the address that is the 10th argument of Printf
事实确实如此
and we see that that is what happened
我们输出了a
we output a
然后将1写入到了printf的第十个参数处
we then write one to the pointer that is the 10th argument to printf
在这里，就是这个指针print_flag
which in this case is this pointer right here print_flag
把它的值设为了1
which sets the value to be 1
就通过了检查
which passes this check
这就是为什么我们看到了flag
and that is why we see flag
其余部分
the rest of this output
是buf中的未初始化数据
is because write is just running on past what was in the flag file
在这个示例中
now in that demo
碰巧有一个指针指向我们想要修改的值
we happen to have a pointer that was pointing to the exact value we wanted to set
而且也不远，所以很容易找到
and it wasn't that far away and so it was pretty easy to find
这很好
and that was great
但如果是其它情况，我们还有哪些利用策略
but what other strategies might we want to consider if that isn't the case
要考虑的一件事是
well one thing to think about is
如果格式化字符串缓冲区在栈上呢
what if our format string buffer is sitting on the stack
我们能控制格式化字符串缓冲区
well we control the format string buffer
因为它是一个格式化字符串漏洞
that's why it's a format string exploit
我们可以在格式化字符串缓冲区中写入一个指针
so we could put a pointer in the format string
它指向我们想要的
and then reference ourselves
或者栈上有一个指针
alternatively there could be a pointer on the stack
它可能不是直接指向我们需要的
it may not point to exactly what we want
但指向一些我们想要影响的
but it may point to something that we might want to influence
因此，看看能访问的指针，还是有必要的
so it's still worth considering in looking at what pointers are available to be accessed
最后一点
and then lastly
想一想RBP的原理
let's think about how base pointers work
栈上保存的RBP指向前一个栈帧的RBP
a saved base pointer points to the prior saved base pointer
能在格式化字符串漏洞利用时，利用这一点
and we can exploit this fact when writing a format string exploit
找到到第一个保存的RBP，这里的ebp1，的距离
by finding the offset to the first saved base pointer in this case ebp one
ebp1将指向一个地址，此处为ebp2
ebp one will be a pointer to a known location in this case ebp two
由此我们可以编写一个格式化字符串漏洞利用
and so we can write a format string exploit
写入数据到ebp1指向的地址，即ebp2
that sets the value that is pointed to by EBP1 to write the value at ebp two
然后，我们就可找到到ebp2的距离（找写入值在第几个参数）
we can then find the format string offset to EBP2
再写入数据到ebp2指向的地址
and write to the address that is pointed to by EBP2
这个地址是我们通过ebp1写入的
which is a value that we wrote from EBP1
我们通过ebp1，将真正想要写入的地址，写到ebp2
and so we use EBP1 to write the address that we really want to write to at ebp2
再通过ebp2写入数据到我们选定的地址
and then use ebp2 to write to anywhere in memory that we decide
通过利用这一点
and by leveraging this
尽管有ASLR，我们还是能写
we have a write that works despite ASLR
我们回过头来
but let's go back
看看格式化字符串缓冲区在栈上会怎样
and look at what happens if our buffer is on the stack
我们可以写入一个指针
and we can put a valid pointer into it
在这个关于ebp的例子中
so in this example here with the base pointers
我们在栈上往回找
we are looking up the stack
查看了前一个栈帧
we are looking at prior stack frames
但当printf被调用时
but when printf is called
发生了什么
what happens
格式化字符串下会有一个栈帧（不是紧挨着）
there's going to be a stack frame below the format string
这意味着
and what this means is that
应该能找到从RSP到格式化字符串缓冲区的偏移量
we should be able to find an offset from RSP to the format string buffer
我不打算在这个视频中解决这个问题
now I'm not going to solve this problem in this video
但是这和我们寻找返回地址的时候很相似
but it's going to be very similar to when we are finding return addresses
和缓冲区溢出时找，到返回地址的偏移，相似
or offsets to a return address in a buffer overflow
那时我们用的pwncyclic
in that case we used pwncyclic
pwncyclic并不能解决这个问题
now pwncyclic will not solve this exact problem
但逻辑是相通的
but a similar type of logic will
使用%n时，演示中没展示的，另一个问题
another problem with using percent n that wasn't in the demo
是%n默认只能写4字节
is that percent n by default writes 4 bytes
但如果我想写8字节呢
what if I want to set 8 bytes
我可以用%ln
well I could use percent ln
要是想写2字节呢
or I need to set 2 bytes
则可用%hn
well that would be percent hn
写一个字节呢
and if I need to just write a single byte
只改一字节
just change one
可用%hhn
I could use percent hhn
如何控制写入内容
now how do we control what to write
在演示中，我们只写了一个字节
in the demo we just wrote a single byte
就一个a
there is a single a
如果我想写入一个指定的值呢
what if I need to write a very specific value
我们需要利用printf的另一个特性
well we need to take advantage of another one of Printf's features
也就是填充
which is padding
我们没做这个的ppt
we don't have a slide on this
建议参考printf的man page
so I'd strongly recommend referencing the Printf Man pages
命令为 man 3 printf
which is man 3 printf
现在的情况是
but what we have going on here is
我们有一个char缓冲区
we have a character buffer
还有printf后跟着 % 一个很大的数 x
and then we have printf followed by percent very large number x
这一首个替换符表示
now this first substitution is saying
打印，或者说解析字符数组buf
print or interpret buf which is a character array
字符数组也是一个指针
and a character array is a pointer
把它按十六进制输出
and we're going to interpret it as a hexadecimal value
因为用的是%x
which is why it's x
同时我们提供了一个很长的填充
and we're going to provide it with this very large amount of padding
所以这会在十六进制数前，输出大量的空白字符
so there's going to be a bunch of white space before this hexadecimal value
这些都会输出到标准输出
and we're going to display all of that to standard out
这里printf的第二个替换符是%1$n
the second printf substitution here is percent 1 $ n
这个%1$表示引用第一个参数，即buf
and so the percent 1 $ is we want to reference the first parameter which again is buf
但因为后面是 n
but because we are doing n
所以这个替换符将把已输出字节长度，写入buf
this substitution is writing this number of bytes to buf
这将导致ABCD被写入buf
and this should result in ABCD being set or being written to buf
但这样做肯定是有代价的
but there is certainly a cost to doing this
我们快速看一下
let's take a quick look at it
我这里有一样的示例代码
so I have that exact demo code over here
有char数组 buf
we have our character array buf
有我们的printf
we have our printf
美观起见，我多打印了几个换行符
I'm printing out a few new lines just for prettiness sake
然后输出buf的内容
and then we're going to write out the contents of buf
编译一下
so let's compile that
运行它
and we're going to run this
我不确定录屏能不能录到
now I'm not sure that this captures on video
但在我的终端底部
but at the bottom of my terminal
光标完全失控了，到处乱跳
the cursor is just going utterly wild and bouncing all over the place
我们没有宕机（三连）
and we're not hanging we're not thinking we're not stuck
我们在等这些填充的空格
what we're waiting on is for all of the white space from this padding
在输出十六进制数前，输完
to display on the terminal before a hexadecimal value
我们只能先等输出结束
and so we're just waiting for that output
这里我们看到
and here we see
babbba74
这是buf指针的十六进制输出
this right here is the hexadecimal interpretation of the buf pointer
然后接着几个换行符
then I have a couple new lines
我看到了ABCD
and I see ABCD
这个ABCD是写入buf内容
the ABCD output is the output from writing the contents of buf
所以我们能设置指定的值
so we were able to set that
但能看到这很耗时
but you could see that that took quite a while
这还只是写4字节
and that was only to write 4 bytes
要是我们要写8字节，该怎么办
so what do we do if we need to write 8 bytes
需要写一个完整的地址
I need to write a full address
我们如何处理这些情况
how do we handle some of these other scenarios
答案是结合前面看到的printf的特性
the answer is to combine some of the features that we've seen previously with printf
这是一个printf格式化字符串
so here is a printf format string
它和前面的例子效果完全一样
that does the exact same thing as the previous example
只是它
except it's going to do it
不需要输出那么多的填充空白字符
without outputting nearly as much noise and padding and white space bytes to the terminal
我们快速看一下
let's take a quick look and see how it works
首先是%65x
first we have percent 65 x
它填充65字节，后跟着一个十六进制值
this is going to be 65 bytes of padding followed by a hexadecimal value
然后是%1$hhn
then we're going to percent 1 $ hhn
将值65写入1字节的buf[0]内
so we're going to write a single byte with the value 65
65恰好是大写字母A的ASCII值
now 65 happens to be the numerical representation of capital A
然后重复%c输出1字节，%hhn写一字节
then we are going to repeatedly write percent C followed by writing a byte
这样能让已输出字节总数递增
so that is going to increment the total number of bytes written
最后依次写下 65 66 67 68，即ABCD
so we will be writing 65666768 in sequence which is ABCD
示例代码在这
now I have the example code right here
我们编译它
if we compile it
执行
and give it a run
能看到结果和上一个非常相似
we see that we get the very similar output to the first example
但终端上没了一页又一页的空白填充符号
except I don't get pages and pages of padding and white space flooding across my terminal
但还是能看到ABCD被写到buf中了
but we still see that ABCD is the value written to buf
速度快了很多，垃圾数据少了很多
just significantly faster with much less noise
值得注意的一点是，ABCD是递增的
now one of the things worth noting here is ABCD is a series of increasing values
这样构造格式化字符串相对很简单
so that's relatively easy to construct a format string that will write this
要是我想写DCBA，一串递减的值呢
what if I wanted to write DCBA which would be a series of decreasing bytes
这里需要一点创意
I might have to get a little bit more creative
我们要把它留给观众作为练习（$）
but we're going to leave that as an exercise to the viewer
就在你以为我们讨论完了printf的特性时
and just when you thought we are done talking about the many features of printf
还有一个要讨论的
we have one more to discuss
就是动态填充大小
and that is dynamic padding size
动态填充大小用*指定
dynamic padding size is specified with the star character
它能让你
and what it allows you to do is
不再依靠硬编码指定填充长度
instead of hard coding the number of padding bytes that you need
你能在另一个参数中指定填充长度
you can say the number of padding bytes for this particular substitution is located in another parameter
拿上面的这个例子来说
and so in the example above here
%*10$c
we have percent star 10 $ c
它会把第10个参数当作一个数字
this will take the 10th parameter interpret it as a number
表示需要的
that represents the amount of padding that is needed
在%c表示的单字符前的，填充长度
for the single character that would normally be displayed with percent c
会输出这么多的字节到终端
will output that many bytes to the terminal
下一个是%11$n
next we have percent 11 $ n
这和%n一样
that is going to work just like percent n
会将已输出的字节数写入到给定地址
which will write the number of bytes that were printed out to the terminal
这会把这个计数写到第11个参数指定的地址
we're going to write that count to the memory pointed to by the 11th parameter
这直接能拷贝内存了（10th的值拷到了11th的地址处）
the end result of this interaction is a direct memory copy
但请记住这一点
but keep in mind that
这里不好一次只写一字节
we are not being clever here writing one byte at a time
如果我们要尝试用这种技术复制整个地址
so if we are going to try and copy a whole address using this technique
会输出大量内容
we're going to dump so much content to standard out
使用起来完全不现实
that it becomes completely unrealistic to use
但还是值得注意的，因为你可能会看到它
however it is worth noting because you may see it